Guide to the Ethel Remington Hepburn papers, 1933-1941.
Hepburn, Ethel Remington
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ethel Remington Hepburn papers, 1933-1941.
7759
Ethel Remington Hepburn
0.1 cubic feet
Correspondence
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The collection contains correspondence and other materials related to the early birth control movement in the United States.
A collection of letters and other material related to the promotion of access to birth control during the 1930s and early 1940s. The collection features material from the papers of Ethel Remington Hepburn, including eleven letters signed by Margaret Sanger. It contains 83 pieces dating from 1933-1941, largely signed, typed letters, but also telegrams, article reprints and material generated by the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control and its successors. In addition to the Sanger letters, there is also material signed by such notable early advocates for access to birth control as Stella Hanau, Dr. Marie Pichel Warner, Dr. Clarence Gamble, Caroline K. Simon, and Florence Rose, Margaret Sanger's secretary who later emerged to be quite influential in her own right in the birth control movement and the fight against world hunger.
Much of the correspondence regards attempts to arrange lectures by Hepburn, requests for information for articles on the subject, and proposals for additional articles, including one particular effort by Dr. Gamble to place an article in the "true confessions" market. One segment of the collection also deals with Hepburn's relationship with Dr. Ellaine Elmore, a popular lecturer and radio host on the subject of motherhood during the 1930s, who later went on to author a number of works on psychic phenomena.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ethel Remington Hepburn's early career was on the vaudeville stage, where she formed a lifelong friendship with legendary performer Eva Tanguay. She later became a professional writer, as well as the mother of ten children. She was a long-time supporter of access to birth control.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hepburn, Ethel Remington.; Elmore, Ellaine.; Gamble, Clarence James, 1894-; Hanau, Stella; Rose, Florence.; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966.; Warner, Marie Pichel.; Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau (New York, N.Y.).; Birth Control Federation of America.; National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Telegram from "Brandon" to Mrs. WW Hepburn c/o LF Hepburn suggesting arrangements for tour of clinic, July 26, no year [1933?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photocopy of letter from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control (NCFLBC) letterhead asking her to write letter to Senator Logan in support of H.R. 5978, March 16, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, directing her toward further materials and suggesting visit to clinic., March 16, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, asking for return of endorsement form, which has been detached., April 5, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, thanking her for return of form., April 26, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Margaret Sanger requesting interview for Physical Culture magazine and tour of the clinic., July 18, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, stating unavailability of Margaret Sanger, but suggesting tour of clinic on July 27 with Miss Willa Murray or Mrs. Hazel Zborowski., July 25, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed on NCFLBC letterhead from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn suggesting appointment on August 28, 1933, August 24, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Stella Hanau to Ethel Remington Hepburn on Birth Control Review letterhead regarding material for article on birth control, August 30, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Mrs. Robert S. Huse (P.B.P. Huse) to Ethel Remington Hepburn on National Committee on Maternal Health letterhead, regarding literature sent for article, September 7, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, thanking her for receipt of article "What Are Ten Children Worth?", October 7, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Stella Hanau to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, inquiring about article for The Forum, January 2, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Stella Hanau explaining that article has not been sold, January 3, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, asking for support of H.R. 5978, March 16, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, thanking her for receipt of article for Modern Living, September 28, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, asking if Hepburn would be interested in lecturing for NCFLBC, December 31, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, responding to offer from Hepburn to lobby for organization, February 4, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose (secretary to Sanger) to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, regarding lecturing by Hepburn, March 29, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, regarding Modern Living article, September 21, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Copy of typed letter to David Victor, managing editor of Modern Living from Florence Rose, regarding photographs for article, September 21, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Stella Hanau to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, regarding Modern Living article, September 30, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Margaret Sanger to Ethel Remington Hepburn on Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau (BCCRB) letterhead, regarding "plan" by Hepburn, October 9, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on NCFLBC letterhead, regarding meeting with Drs. Warner and Stone, October 12, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Marie Pichel Warner to Ethel Remington Hepburn regarding appointment, November 7, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Typed letter signed from Marie Pichel Warner to Ethel Remington Hepburn regarding plans for Hepburn to work up article on Warner's "Sex Series" at New York University, November 25, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reprint of article from Medical Journal and Record, "The Problem of Contraception" by Marie Pichel Warner (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reprint of article from The Medical Woman's Journal, "Birth Control and Sex Attitudes in All Countries" by Marie Pichel Warner, July, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Reprint of New York Times article "Group to 'Debunk' 'Myth of Mothers'" which mentions Dr. Ellaine Elmore, October 17, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Reprint of New York Times article "Dr. Alfred Adler Will Speak Here" which mentions Dr. Ellaine Elmore (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Typed letter signed from David Cole of Psychology Magazine to Ethel Remington Hepburn requesting assistance in how to respond to letter from reader wanting birth control information, January 27, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Copy of letter referenced above (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Typed letter signed from David Cole to Ethel Remington Hepburn, thanking Hepburn for response to previous request, with reference to Stella Hanau of the American Birth Control League (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Typed letter signed from David Cole to Ethel Remington Hepburn, regarding Dr. Ellaine Elmore and a project to create a "Psychological Resting Home" for mothers, soliciting speaking engagement for Dr. Elmore, and mentioning Sunday evening meetings, undated [December 16, 1934] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Copy of letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to David Cole, in response to above, offering use of Hepburn's name on stationary, December 19, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Typed letter from David Cole to Ethel Remington Hepburn, regarding "things badly misrepresented" by Dr. Elmore, and withdrawal of support of Psychology Magazine, undated [early 1935?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Typed letter signed, two pages, from David Cole to Ethel Remington Hepburn further detailing reservations about Dr. Elmore's identity and desires to use meetings for "self-promotion, financial and otherwise", undated [1935] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Handwritten letter, two pages, from Ellaine Elmore to Ethel Remington Hepburn, requesting talk, December 30, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Handwritten letter, one page recto and verso, from Ellaine Elmore to Ethel Remington Hepburn, inviting Hepburn to speak at January 20, 1935 Sunday Evening Meeting at the Iroquois Hotel, January 6, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Handwritten letter, one page recto and verso, from Ellaine Elmore to Ethel Remington Hepburn confirming talk and referring to Hepburn's "gifted child", January 12, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Autograph letter signed, one page recto and verso, from Ellaine Elmore to Ethel Remington Hepburn, January 16, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Copy of typed letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Ellaine Elmore, withdrawing permission to use name, February 7, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Typed letter signed, with corrections, two pages, from Ellaine Elmore to Ethel Remington Hepburn in response to letter above, February 10, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCCRB letterhead, stating intentions not to go ahead with plans discussed, March 16, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCCRB letterhead, regarding Hepburn's interest in a part time job, forwarding of Hepburn's letter of March 19 to Margaret Sanger, March 25, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCCRB letterhead, raising possibility of Hepburn creating "True Stories" type article on birth control "saving you from untold calamities." Not attached indicating idea for the article came from Dr. Clarence Gamble, April 1, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Carbon copy of letter, two pages, from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Florence Rose, regarding difficulties of publishing this type of article, with examples of prior editors objecting to birth control content. Willingness stated to still attempt if remuneration is sufficient, April 4, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typed letter signed from Dr. Clarence Gamble to Florence Rose, further discussing potential article, with suggestions on how to make it "adequately pornographic", April 7, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCCRB letterhead, referring to notes from Margaret Sanger (no longer attached) and Dr. Gamble's proposition, April 11, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Carbon copy of typed letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Dr. Clarence Gamble, responding to Gamble's suggestions, April 18, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typed letter signed from Dr. Clarence Gamble to Ethel Remington Hepburn in response to hers of April 18, above, April 20, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typed letter signed on BCCRB letterhead with handwritten notes from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn, regarding appointment with Margaret Sanger, May 31, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typed letter signed from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Florence Rose on Hepburn's personal stationary, with handwritten notes from Florence Rose, regarding appointment with Margaret Sanger, June 3, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Telegram from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn, canceling appointment, June 6, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCCRB letterhead, regarding interest in providing lectures, March 2, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Carbon copy of typed letter to Florence Rose from Ethel Remington Hepburn, regarding interest in lecturing, March 3, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copy of form letter from Margaret Sanger on BCCRB letterhead, soliciting members to join the Committee on Public Progress for Birth Control, November 30, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copy of form letter from Margaret Sanger on BCCRB letterhead, two pages, soliciting letters to Katherine Lenroot. Second page has an information sheet to guide letter writers (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copy of typed letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Katherine Lenroot, regarding support for birth control, December 13, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Katherine Lenroot on US Department of Labor, Children's Bureau, letterhead, in reply to December 13 letter (above), December 14, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCCRB letterhead, regarding appointment with Margaret Sanger, December 17, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copy of form letter from Margaret Sanger soliciting letters to magazines requesting articles on birth control, January 39, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copy of typed letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to McCall's magazine, asking if there is any interest in a birth control article, January 30, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on Birth Control Federation of America (BCFA) letterhead, noting change in name of the organization and apologizing for delay in responding to inquiry, February 7, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Florence Rose, with handwritten notes by Rose in reply, August 12, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed notice regarding the Committee on Public Progress of the BCCRB now being part of the BCFA, with handwritten notes by Ethel Remington Hepburn regarding submissions to magazine, August 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Edward Weeks, editor of Atlantic Magazine regarding comments on birth control, August 16, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Florence rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCFA letterhead, regarding appointment with Margaret Sanger, October 4, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Four page form letter from BCFA, soliciting letters to be sent to Atlantic Magazine in response to birth control articles, October 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copy of typed letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Edward Weeks, responding to his letter of August 16 and offering comments on birth control, October 6, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCFA letterhead, responding to letter of February 22, 1940, granting permission to deviate from monthly letter suggestions, March 4, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Florence Rose to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCFA letterhead, accepting Hepburn's resignation from Public Progress Committee, October 30, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Darrell Huff, associate editor of Look Magazine to Ethel Remington Hepburn, thanking her for comments on Margaret Sanger article in magazine, August 22, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Five typed letters signed, stapled together, from Caroline K. Simon, editor of Birth Control Review to Ethel Remington Hepburn on BCFA letterhead, regarding article submitted to the Review, August 17, 1939 - November 8, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Form letter from BCFA Committee on Public Progress, requesting letter be sent to Atlantic Magazine commending them on birth control articles, November 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Four page form letter from BCFA Committee on Public Progress, requesting letters be sent to Eleanor Roosevelt, with copies of news accounts of her remarks on birth control, January 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copy of letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to BCFA Committee on Public Progress, declining request to send letters to Eleanor Roosevelt, February 22, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copy of letter from Ethel Remington Hepburn to Franklin D. Roosevelt, supporting a federal government role in providing birth control services, May 14, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Jay du Von of the Works Projects Administration to Ethel Remington Hepburn, in response to Hepburn's letter to F.C. Harrington of the Administration regarding birth control services, June 28, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Typed letter signed from Mabel Wager, BCFA Committee on Public Progress, to Ethel Remington Hepburn, accepting Hepburn's resignation from the Committee, January 10, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Printed card with handwritten corrections. Invitation to attend meeting of New Jersey Birth Control League. Address of Mrs. Enos Metzel handwritten on verso (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Autograph letter signed from Maud Messler to Ethel Remington Hepburn, one page recto and verso, regarding setting up appointment to view Trenton clinic, February 13, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Autograph letter signed from Alice Lindabury to Ethel Remington Hepburn, regarding visit to Trenton clinic, February 17, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)